A Guide to the Olney Winsor Letters, 1786-1788
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Olney Winsor Letters, 1786-1788
Library of Virginia
21137, 22754
.1 cubic feet
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Accession 21137 purchased from James A. Tyson, Old and Rare Books, 319 Caesar Michigan Boulevard, Providence, Rhode Island, 21 January 1937.
Accession 22764 purchased from the John Carter Brown Library, Providence, Rhode Island, through the Rhode Island Historical Society, 1947.
Biographical Information
Olney Winsor was born 24 August 1753 in Providence, Rhode Island, to Samuel Winsor (1722-1803) and Lydia Olney (1726-1753). He became a successful merchant in Rhode Island. Winsor married first Freelove Waterman 30 November 1777, and they had four children. He married second Hope Thurber, and they had one child. Winsor died in Providence 15 March 1837.
Scope and Content
Letters, 1786-1788, from Olney Winsor (1753-1837) of Providence, Rhode Island, and temporarily living in Alexandria, Virginia, to his wife, Hope Winsor, in Providence discussing his journey to Alexandria, social and religious life in Alexandria, as well as his business concerns as a merchant. Winsor comments on personal and family matters. Winsor writes about his legal entanglement over a condemned brig which required him to travel to Williamsburg, Virginia, and he describes the towns of Fredericksburg and Richmond, Virginia, and Williamsburg as he travelled through them. Winsor comments on a local election in Alexandria, politics in Rhode Island, and Maryland's ratification of the federal Constitution. He mentions a fire in Richmond in January 1787, comments on funerals in Alexandria, and remarks on Virginia Episcopalians. Winsor describes a dinner he attended with George Washington at which they discussed the new federal Constitution. Also includes a memorandum of his return voyage from Alexandria to Providence.
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Olney Winsor, Papers, 1808-1847. Accession 36202; Misc. Reel 58. Personal papers collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
Contents List
- Letter, 2 September 1786, from Winsor to his wife describing his voyage from Providence to Alexandria, mentioning whom he has met, and sending his love to his family., 2 pages.
- Letter, 7, 11, 16, 17, 18, 20, 27 September and 1 October 1786, from Winsor to his wife commenting on his boarding house, the weather, religious services he attended and family matters., 4 pages.
- Letter, 4 October 1786, from Winsor to his wife commenting on his health, friends, and family., 1 leaf.
- Letter, 5 October 1786, from Winsor to his wife stating that Captain Wheaton has arrived and sending love to his family., 1 leaf.
- Letter, 9 October 1786, from Winsor to his wife stating that he is sending items by way of Captain Wheaton, noting that the Alexandria horse races are commencing, and commenting on his business., 2 pages.
- Letter, 17 October 1786, from Winsor to his wife commenting on her health, his desire to see his family, and items he has sent home. Winsor comments on Rhode Island politics and difficulties in the state., 4 pages.
- Letter, 12 November 1786, from Winsor to his wife stating that he will be travelling to Williambsurg, Virginia, to attend a trial concerning a brig and its cargo that he has an interest in., 1 leaf.
- Letter, 27 November 1786, from Winsor to his wife concerning her health and his family. He mentions the death of his grandmother., 2 pages.
- Letter, 28 November 1786, from Winsor to his wife regarding his absence from home, his wife's letter writing, the rent for the home, and other family news., 3 pages.
- Letter, 5 December 1786, from Winsor to his wife describing his journey from Alexandria to Williamsburg and back., 4 pages.
- Letter, 9, 10, 11, 16, 17, 19 December 1786, from Winsor to his wife concerning their health and family news. He also comments on his business, including the unloading and loading of cargo for shipment., 4 pages.
- Letter, 19 December 1786, from Winsor to his wife thanking her for the gifts sent and mentioning items he sent to her. Winsor also comments on his health and his business., 1 leaf.
- Letter, 20 December 1786, from Winsor to his wife commenting on his daughter Nancy's education., 1 leaf.
- Letter, 10, 11 January 1786 [1787], from Owen Winsor, Alexandria, Virginia, to his wife, Hope Winsor, Providence, Rhode Island, commenting on his activities in Alexandria and stating that he misses his wife and family., 3 pages.
- Letter, 18 July [January], 19 January 1787, from Winsor, Williamsburg, to his wife concerning his treatment in Alexandria, the necessity for another journey to Williamsburg concerning the trial relating to the brig and its cargo, and fire which swept through Richmond 15 January 1787., 3 pages.
- Letter, 26 January 1787, from Winsor, Alexandria, to his wife concerning the trial for the brig and family news., 1 leaf.
- Letter, 7, 13, 18, 22 February, 2, 3, 4, 6 March 1787, from Winsor to his wife commenting on the trial concerning the brig, Rhode Island politics, Alexandria politics and elections, prostitution and women in Alexandria, funerals, African Americans, and personal news., 6 pages.
- Letter, 18, 19 February 1787, from Winsor to his wife concerning family and business matters., 3 pages.
- Letter, 23 March 1787, from Winsor to his wife discussing the condemnation of the brig and the fate of its cargo, as well as business and personal news., 3 pages.
- Letter, 27 March 1787, from Winsor to his wife discussing his business dealings and family news., 3 pages.
- Letter, 29 March 1787, from Winsor to his wife concerning his fitting of the brig for sailing and thanking her for clothes she sent., 1 leaf.
- Letter, 1 April 1787, from Winsor to his wife stating that he is shipping her some flour and cloth and adding he hopes to be home in May, but is uncertain. Winsor also sends family and personal news., 3 pages.
- Letter, 2 April 1787, from Winsor to his wife sending his love to the family and asking her to forward a letter (not present) to his father., 1 leaf.
- Letter, 2 April 1787, from Winsor to his wife discussing his wife's his daughter's and his own health and commenting on his possible return to Providence., 3 pages.
- Letter, 6 April 1787, from Winsor to his wife stating that he had bought most of the sugar and coffee from the brig's cargo ordered sold., 2 pages.
- Letter, 4 January 1788, from Winsor to his wife informing her that he has arrived in Alexandria after a long sea voyage and stating many arrived at his store to see him., 2 pages.
- Letter, 9, 13 January 1788, from Winsor to his wife providing more details about his voyage from Providence to Alexandria., 4 pages.
- Letter, 25 January 19 February 1788, from Winsor to a friend in Baltimore, Maryland, discussing the Rhode Island governor's view of the federal Constitution. He also comments on Episcopalians and Methodists in Virginia., 2 pages.
- Letter, 4 February 1788, from Winsor to his wife commenting on a fire in Alexandria which threatened his store, and that the Potomac River is closed because of ice. He adds that he hopes for more letters from home and sends family and personal news., 2 pages.
- Letter, 10 March 1788, from Winsor to his wife concerning his health and business, commenting on his daughter's education, and sending personal and family news., 2 pages.
- Letter, 18 March 1788, from Winsor to his wife reflecting on death and commenting on personal, family and business news., 4 pages.
- Letter, 21, 22, 23, 24, 25 March 1788, from Winsor to his wife commenting on family matters, including noting that he has written his father and brother. Winsor comments on friends, business, and his health. He adds that he has sent a book for his daughter., 3 pages.
- Letter, 31 March 5 April 1788, from Winsor to his wife commenting on George Washington and the Constitution. He also mentions news from Providence that he has seen., 2 pages, incomplete.
- Letter, 31 March 4, 5, 8, 10, 17, 18, 19 April 1788, from Winsor to his wife describing a dinner he attended with George Washington. He comments on the new federal Constitution and Virginia's stand. Winsor also sends personal and business news. This is accession 22764., 16 leaves, positive and negative photostats.
- Letter, 26, 27, 28, 29 April 1788, from Winsor to his wife thanking her for items sent and mentioning items he has sent to her. Winsor mentions that Maryland has adopted the Constition. He asks after family and sends personal news., 3 pages.
- Letter, 3, 4, 5 May 1788, from Winsor to his wife commenting on his social life in Alexandria and mentioning that he had been to Sunday meeting., 3 pages.
- Letter, 8 May 1788, from Winsor to his wife sending social news and asking after the family., 2 pages.
- Letter, 11, 16, 18, 19, 20, 21 May 1788, from Winsor to his wife commenting on his social life and his religious life, and discussing his business affairs., 3 pages.
- Memorandum, 10, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21 June 1788, of Winsor's voyage from Alexandria, Virginia, to Providence, Rhode Island., 4 pages.